Guide to the Emma Goldman Papers, 1909-1941 and undated RL.11353
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters, 1909-1941 and undated; 1
  - E. Colton [Emma Goldman] (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1927 January 24; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman updates Keell on the raffle being held for Freedom, then asks him to edit her report for use in Freedom.
  - Emma Goldman? (Winnipeg, Canada) to H. Lynch (Toronto, Canada), 1927 February 5; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman refuses Lynch's invitation to debate.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1927 March 26; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman reports that attendance to her lectures in Winnipeg was poor, in contrast to Edmonton, Alberta, where she had great success. She settles her accounts regarding the sale of literature. She outlines plans for more lectures in Toronto, and the possibility of remaining in Canada an additional year. She comments on Sectarianism in the movement and wishes she had more information on China for her lecture. She reports on the raffle that should garner $50 for Freedom. She then orders more literature.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1927 April 9; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman sends a report for Freedom on her lectures, and asks Keell to especially mention money collected for Russian political prisoners. She then outlines possible plans for remaining in Canada. She reports that she has been unable to sell their pamphlet on the Labour report, and plans to sell them shortly at a steep discount.
  - E. Colton [Emma Goldman] (Toronto, Canada) to Evelyn [Metcalfe?] (n.p.), 1927 April 14; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 36 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes a report on her activities in Canada, and adds that she will not be returning to Europe for the foreseeable future. She then discusses where she is able to publish her articles, since she cannot do so in American papers or magazines. She notes she is forced to succeed through lecturing. She reports that there is a plan to raise money to support her in writing her autobiography, but she has no faith in it. She plans to read Elmer Gantry, by Sinclair Lewis.
    Anarchism -- Canada; Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (London, England), 1927 April 20; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman revises her total collected on behalf of Russian political prisoners and states that she will be remaining in Canada for the year.
  - E. Colton [Emma Goldman] (Toronto, Canada) to John L. Counsell (Hamilton, Canada), 1927 May 25; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 36 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes about Russian imperialism and the success of anarchist and communist movements, particularly in Great Britain. She adds that " After all there were two revolutions in Russia. We have therefore a right to expect a higher ethical conception and a more humane attitude towards human life as we demand of imperialistic and capitalistic countries."
    Imperialism -- History -- 20th century; Anarchism -- Great Britain; Communism -- Great Britain; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - E. Colton [Emma Goldman] (Toronto, Canada) to Comrade (n.p.), 1927 May 26; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 36 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes that she is grateful to know that her work has been helpful to these two Chinese comrades, but states that she is too poor to travel to China at this point in time, however much she would like to see the country "in its present great struggle." She describes the theoretical vs. active approaches to Anarchism, and their relationship to Chinese anarchists. She feels that the spiritual, intellectual, and economic awakening in China deserve the support of Anarchists, if only to avoid the dictatorship that has occurred in Russia. She adds that she cannot supply the reading material the writers request, because most of it was confiscated by the authorities in New York. She announces that Berkman is writing a book on Anarchism.
    Anarchism -- China; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1927 June 26; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman asks why Keell has not written, and encloses $25 raised for the support of Freedom. She loosely outlines her plans for staying and lecturing in Canada, then notes that she is considering writing an autobiography. She is planning on writing her lectures for the summer and requests books.
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Anarchism -- Canada; Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1927 June 27; 2 Leaves; 3 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In response to Keell's statement, Goldman records what little literature has sold, and the payments she has made.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (London, England), 1926 July 31; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In a postcard, Goldman supplies her new address, then orders more literature for her lectures.
  - [Emma Goldman] (n.p.) to Heywood Broun (New York City), 1927 August 26; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman? expresses her admiration for Broun's courage and writing on the Sacco-Vanzetti case.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Broun, Heywood, 1888-1939
  - E. Colton [Emma Goldman] (Toronto, Canada) to Rosa Sacco (Boston, Massachusetts), 1927 September 3; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman admits that she is proud Nic and Vanzetti spoke about her, but she cannot remember an actual meeting with them. She encloses a letter she wrote to them, then requests biographical information to be used in a pamphlet about the two. She reports on a memorial held in Toronto.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Sacco, Rose; Sacco, Nicola, 1891-1927; Vanzetti, Bartolomeo, 1888-1927
  - E. Colton [Emma Goldman] (Toronto, Canada) to Evelyn Scott (Staten Island, N.Y.), 1927 September 3; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 35 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman explains that her time has been taken up by the Sacco and Vanzetti case, and her deep disappointment in the outcome. However, she sees two areas for hope. One is that Sacco and Vanzetti will be heroes, the other that the American intelligentsia came out in defense of the two men.
    Sacco-Vanzetti Trial, Dedham, Mass., 1921; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom Keell (n.p.), 1927 September 14; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman reports that she has been diagnosed with inflammation of the spinal nerves and is being treated with "violet rays,' which is helping. She encloses her letter to Evelyn Scott on the Sacco and Vanzetti case for Keell's use in Freedom. She comments on the Labour Party and the compromises it will have to make when in office, and states that she has lost all faith in the workers.
    Sacco-Vanzetti Trial, Dedham, Mass., 1921; Labour Party (Great Britain); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom Keell (n.p.), 1927 September 19; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman asks for pamphlets and copies of Freedom for her lectures and outlines a plan to get them past customs.
    Anarchism -- Periodicals; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom Keell (London, England), 1927 October 15; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes in a postcard that the literature she ordered has been arriving safely, although literature sales have been very poor.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom Keell (London, England), 1927 November 11; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 36 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman requests that Keell stop sending literature. Attendance has been so poor at her lectures there is no way to sell literature. She must finish the series to which she is committed, but she is hopeless about its success. She comments on the amnesty in Russia that has come and gone with no hope for the political prisoners, and wonders if she should have stayed in Russia to do her work. In a postscript, she asks Keell if he thinks she would be successful in London lecturing on general topics, rather than just on Russia.
    Anarchism -- Periodicals; Anarchism -- Canada; Political persecution -- Soviet Union -- History; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1927 December 27; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes that she has over three hundred pamphlets left over that she cannot possibly sell, along with some books. She plans to give the books as gifts, then approach the Road to Freedom about selling the pamphlets. Her meetings have not been profitable, so she has had to borrow money for her expenses, and at this point does not even have money for a passage to Europe. She admits she is sorry that Freedom will be closing down, and wishes she knew what to suggest.
    Anarchism -- Periodicals; Anarchism -- Canada; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Toronto, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 January 25; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman describes her final weeks in Canada, as well as how she distributed the literature she had on hand. She outlines her plans for heading back to Europe, then comments on other presenters reaping benefits from the lectures she has done.
  - Emma Goldman (Montreal, Canada) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 February 26; 3 Leaves; 5 pages; 18 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman reports on the end of her stay in Canada and on the final arrangements for the last of the pamphlets in Canada. She requests more books for her use., and on her plans for her autobiography, along with the research needed for it.
    Anarchism -- Canada; Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 March 3; 2 Leaves; 5 pages; 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman provides instructions for remaindering publications in Keell's files. She comments on charges made against him by others in the movement, "Anarchism would be a beautiful ideal, if it were not for the anarchists." She then mentions two comrades who have died suddenly. She closes with a discussion of the memoirs she ordered.
    Anarchism -- Periodicals; Anarchists; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (London, England), 1928 March 12; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In a postcard, Goldman writes about an appeal that Keell has drafted, considering that it should go to America and Canada, along with Europe.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 March 15; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman reports that she will make an appeal to a person visiting her on behalf of Freedom.
  - E. G. Colton [Emma Goldman] (Paris?, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 April 16; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes about a gathering she has convened to which she invites [William C.] Owen and Keell. She also comments on the books she ordered.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Owen, William C.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 May 2; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman wonders if Keell received her last letter. She announces that she is coming to London for a week, and wishes to meet the new team for Freedom.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 May 14; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman orders a copy of Laura Riding's "Anarchism is not Enough." She comments that younger blood is needed to support Freedom via a circulating letter. She then requests payment for any copies of "My Disillusionment" Keell has on hand.
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Riding, Laura, 1901-1991
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (London, England), 1928 May 23; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 10 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In a postcard, Goldman thanks Keell for the books received and then provides her new address. She asks whether the circulating letter has been sent yet.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 July 30; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman requests data for her autobiography.
    Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1928 September 29; 3 Leaves; 4 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes about the divisions in the anarchist movement that keep it from growing. She hopes Keell's plan for monthly indoor lectures succeeds. She requests more information for her book and discusses its progress. She then requests he send her another book.
    Anarchism; Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Joseph (n.p.), 1928 October 26; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman discusses the difficulties she faces in writing her book, and requests and extension on a book chapter she promised to write. She adds a brief history of birth control in the United States.
    Autobiographies; Birth control -- United States; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Harry [Kelly?] (n.p.), 1928 October 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes about the difficulty she has had in getting information for her book regarding specific individuals. She then requests a copy of a book, and notes that Berkman has finished writing his most recent book.
    Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Kelly, Harry, 1871-1953; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - [Emma Goldman] (Paris, France) to Mr. Holmes (n.p.), 1929 January 7; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes that she and Holmes will never see eye to eye on Russia, because he will accept no proofs for criticism of the regime, and he does not separate the State from Society.
    Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1929 February 3; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman notes progress made on her book, and comments on the closing of Freedom's London office, despite the increasing interest in the newspaper: " I wish I knew whether it is due to our methods of propaganda, or to the general reaction in the world, that there is so little interest in Anarchism." She then outlines her travel plans.
    Autobiographies; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to William C. Owen (Storrington, England), 1929 June 19; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes about Owen's health concerns and asks if he would permit her to raise a private subscription for him.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Owen, William C.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1929 July 26; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 10 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In a postcard, Goldman thanks Keell for sending articles written by William C. Owen, and then recommends others he can approach for information regarding Owen, who has died.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom H. Keell (Near Stroud., England), 1929 November 30; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Goldman writes that she is completely focused on her book, to the exclusion of other matters, including writing an article regarding William C. Owen. She suggests he approach someone else. She then discusses when her manuscript is due and the advance she would like to use to settle her debts with Keell.
    Anarchists; Labor unions -- Soviet Union; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Owen, William C.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1930 May 14; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman announces that all their plans have been disrupted. Berkman has been deported to Belgium and she has been working for his right to reenter. The rest of the letter concerns an attack made on Keell in Freedom. Goldman thinks personal grievances have no place in the paper, but plans to protest the attack anyway. "I really feel most unhappy over our trouble and the general condition in our ranks, the vindictive]ness, the wrangles, they are sickening."
    Deportation -- France -- History -- 20th century; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1930 May 19; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman writes to arrange a meeting with Keell, [Max?] Nettlau, and [Alexander?] Shapiro. They will possibly discuss a joint protest to Freedom regarding the attack on Keell.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1930 June 10; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman writes that the protest to Freedom is complete, and is on its way to Rudolf Rocker in London for his signature and forwarding to the paper. She adds that Berkman has returned. She plans to leave for Germany.
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Rocker, Rudolf, 1873-1958
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1930 June 29; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman recommends that Keell wait for the August issue to appear before enquiring about their protest. She also advises him to also grive the "new group" access to the Freedom plant, to help end the personal squabbles.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1930 July 27; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman again counsels Keell to wait for the protest to appear, and to settle the matter privately.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1930 December 21; 3 Leaves; 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman congratulates Keell on his restrained tone in response to the attack on him. She outlines her work to complete her autobiography, although she must wait a year for it to be published. She hopes to do more for Freedom Press in the coming year.
    Autobiographies; Freedom Press (London, England); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1931 January 15; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman requests a pamphlet and point of information she requires to complete her book.
  - [Emma Goldman] (St. Tropez, France) to "old Scout" (n.p.), 1931 February 1; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman reports that she has finished her book, and requests that it be given a serious reading. She also reports that Berkman has been granted a stay, with renewals. She adds that she will soon travel to Nice.
    Autobiographies; Deportation -- France -- History -- 20th century; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - [Emma Goldman] (Nice, France) to Joseph [Ishill] (n.p.), 1931 February 13; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman notes that Alexander Berkman has been permitted to stay in the country and that she has completed her book, although she is suffering with extreme pain in her heels. She recommends sources of information on Voltairine de Cleyre. She comments on the respect that Knopf has shown her autobiography. Finally, she writes that she would like to meet Elie Faure.
    Deportation -- France -- History -- 20th century; Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Ishill, Joseph.; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; De Cleyre, Voltairine, 1866-1912
  - Emma Goldman (Nice, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1931 February 19; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman announces that she has finished her book, but discusses her physical issues. She requests that Keell send a copy of her essays to a Polish group publishing an encyclopedia of Yiddish writers. She then comments on George Davison's death.
    Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Davison, George, 1854-1930
  - [Emma Goldman] (Nice, France) to Evelyn [Metcalfe?] (n.p.), 1931 March 10; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman reports on finishing her book, and that doing so has deeply fatigued her. She adds that she is in Nice only temporarily, because of the expense. She then comments on Clifford McCarthy, a recent acquaintance.
    Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - [Emma Goldman] (St. Tropez, France) to "Good Comrade" (n.p.) [Max Nettlau?], 1931 May 13; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman despairs "the difficulty of getting to any understanding by means of letters." Topics include the treatment of Rysanov by Soviet authorities, anarchism as a progressive cause, the lack of stress on preparing individuals and the masses for what comes after the Revolution, her sense that she is useless and unable to be in touch with the masses, the revolution in Spain compared to the Russian revolution, and her inability to attend the Syndicalist Congress in Spain.
    Political persecution -- Soviet Union -- History; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936; Anarchism; Spain -- Politics and government -- 1931-1939; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Nettlau, Max, 1865-1944
  - [Emma Goldman] (St. Tropez, France) to "Friends" [Mark and Johanna], 1931 June 6; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman writes of feeling fatigued following the completion of her book, and discusses first paper to do a story on her autobiography and its Yiddish translation, and the final release of the 2-volume set. She comments on the Spanish Republic and reports on Alexander Berkman's activities.
    Autobiographies; Spain -- Politics and government -- 1931-1939; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1931 June 12; 4 Leaves; 5 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman writes to ask Keell what books he has loaned her should be returned. She comments on the failure of Knopf's London office, and on George Davison's estate, and her plans to read Max Nettlau's latest book. In a postscript she comments on the Freedom Bulletin, wondering if it still exists.
    Freedom bulletin (London, England); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Davison, George, 1854-1930
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1931 October 9; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman writes of her travel plans, Alexander Berkman's medical condition, the release of her autobiography, and the puzzle that is her future plans.
    Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1931 December 1; 5 Leaves; 5 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman outlines the possibility of a European speaking tour, then comments on her autobiography -- the British edition, favorable reviews, the high cost of the volumes, and review copies.
    Anarchism -- Europe; Autobiographies; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (St. Tropez, France) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1932 October 27; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Goldman writes about the British edition of her autobiography, and her possible plans to come to London
  - Emma Goldman (The Hague, Netherlands) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1933 January 23; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)